中美洲
旁白：大脑袋和中空的骨骼使它们能
NARRATOR: With huge brains and hollow bones,
翱翔于天际
they navigate the canopy
每一个细胞
Every cell
都是为了飞翔而存在
is engineered for flight.
它们有自己的语言
They speak a language all their own
也有可以维持80年的情感关系
and form lifelong bonds that can last for 80 years.
它们的翅膀可以带他们
Their wings can carry them
每天飞翔50英里
50 miles in a day.
世界各地都遍及着它们的足迹
This is a creature who lives without borders,
我们对它们了解甚少
in a world we can hardly fathom,
但却有上百万的它们和我们人类生活在一起
and yet millions live among us.
这是它们的故事
This is their story.
纪录片之家字幕组倾情奉献
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
=======================
http://www.jlpzj.net
翻译：21st@纪录片之家
校对：邓不疑@纪录片之家
======================
当圣巴巴拉市刚刚进入黎明
NARRATOR: As day breaks over Santa Barbara,
风头鹦鹉多利
a cockatoo named Dolly
就开始呼唤她的同类
calls to her flock.
哇哦 多利
WOMAN: Oh, Dolly.
早上好 小美鸟
Good morning pretty bird,
good morning pretty bird,
小美鸟 你一大早上起来就这么活泼哈？
pretty girl, you're just up and all sparky, huh?
-多利：我是一只小美鸟
-嗨
-DOLLY: I'm a pretty bird.
-Hi!
多利一般早上6点30或7点就起床
Dolly likes to wake up about 6:30 or 7:00 in the morning.
想来点早餐不？
Want some breakfast?
-多利：嗨 小美鸟 -嗨 小美鸟
-DOLLY: Hi, pretty bird! -Hi, pretty bird.
我得赶紧在它吵醒所有邻居前开始照顾它
I rush to get her before she wakes up all the neighbors.
我的邻居们人都很好 我可不想把他们赶跑
They're very nice people and I want to keep it that way.
多利在叫
[Dolly squawking]
旁白：风头鹦鹉的声音
NARRATOR:With voices designed
足以穿越森林 因此它的叫声对大多数人来说
to each across the forest,cockatoos can be a challenge
是一个很大的挑战
for the average homeowner.
米歇尔：它的叫声真的很大
MICHEL: The screaming is really hard.
让我最终不得不用上了射击耳塞
I finally got gun range earphones.
叫
[Squawking]
即使戴上耳塞也不能完全阻隔这个叫声
And that doesn't completely deaden it.
你仍然可以听见声音 只是叫声不会再震疼你的耳膜
You can still hear it, it just doesn't make your eardrums hurt.
多利当时在一个鸟类展览上
Dolly was in a bird collection,
而那位男士还没完全准备好
and the gentleman just wasn't really ready
领养一只摩鹿加风头鹦鹉
to deal with a Moluccan cockatoo.
当我见到她时 她有点情绪不稳定
She was sort of damaged when I got her, emotionally.
我的朋友把我带去
I had a friend that took me over there
看看我愿不愿意领养多利
to see if I wanted to adopt Dolly.
然后我看了看她 她也看了看我
And I just took one look at her and she took one look at me
我知道我没得选了
and I knew I had no choice, you know.
她会成为我的鹦鹉
She was gonna be mine.
我领养她时她才三岁
She was three when I got her,
到三月她就在我家呆了16年了
it'll be 16 years in March.
她能活八九十岁
She is going to live to be 80 or 90.
而我现在已经74岁了 所以
And I am 74, so, that's --
我们俩在一起的日子不会太多了
we don't have many more years together.
而我-- 她是我最关心的事
And I'm for--That's my biggest concern.
我走哪都会带着多利
I take Dolly everywhere I can.
她喜欢坐车
She loves going in the car.
我猜是因为坐车的感觉很像飞翔
I think it's an experience probably like flying.
你知道的 看着街景快速闪过的感觉
You know, they see the scenery rushing by.
多利在叫
[Dolly chattering]
旁白：多利正在去当地的一家保护所
NARRATOR: Dolly's headed to a local sanctuary,
她每周都会去那呆几天
where she boards a few days each week.
这是拉瓦尼亚保证正常生活的策略
This is Lavanya's survival tactic.
当多利在家时，拉瓦尼亚的生活就得围着多利转
When Dolly is at home with Lavanya, it's all about Dolly.
不能打电话 不能有人来家里
There's no talking on the phone, there's no having company.
这样呆个三四天后
And after about three or four days of that,
可怜的拉瓦尼亚也必须处理下自己的事
poor Lavanya has to take care of her own needs, as well.
当心头
Watch you head!
米歇尔：这样我就能赴约并且完成一些事
MICHEL: So I can go to appointments and get things done
也有时间做点
and have a little time to do
我喜欢的事 走访下朋友
some of the things I like to do, visit friends.
-我们要走啦 拜拜-多利：拜拜 小美鸟
-We're gonna go bye-bye!-DOLLY: Bye-bye, pretty bird.
米歇尔：拜拜 小美鸟
MICHEL: Bye-bye, pretty bird!
杰米 我们又回来啦
Hey, Jamie, we're back.
旁白：杰米 麦克劳德 创建了这家圣巴巴罗市鸟类保护所
NARRATOR: Jamie McLeod founded the Santa Barbara Bird Sanctuary
九年前当她发现
nine years ago, when she noticed there was
那些没人要的鹦鹉是个麻烦
a problem with unwanted parrots.
-几天后见-好的
-I'll see you in a couple days.-All right.
早上好多利
Good morning, Dolly!
旁白：她开始意识到
NARRATOR: She began to realize
她当时在卖的很多鸟
many of the birds she was selling
都是第二次出售了
were being re-homed.
麦克劳德：我养了30年的鸟
McLEOD: I was a breeder for more than 30 years.
亚马逊鹦鹉 金刚鹦鹉 风头鹦鹉
Amazons, Macaws, Cockatoos.
人们通常只养两到四年
When people typically would keep the birds two to four years,
很明显
it became apparent
不是每个人都能养的
that not everybody's cracked up to own one.
它们能活到80岁
They live 80 years --
除了长寿
crunch those numbers out
也有很多没人要的鹦鹉
and there's a lot of unwanted parrots out there.
嗨 伙计们
Hi, guys!
我感觉我能做点什么
I felt I was contributing to a problem,
然后开始给没人要的鹦鹉重新找个家
and started focusing on re-homing all the unwanted ones.
男：来吧
MAN: There we go!
麦克劳德：我们现在有
McLEOD: We currently have
60多只鸟
more than 60 birds
已经超出了我们的收养能力
and we're beyond capacity.
我们拒绝了很多人
We're turning people away.
你准备好吃早餐了么？
Okay, you ready for your breakfast?
走吧 美女
Let's go, girl!
麦克劳德：人们把鹦鹉留在门口
McLEOD: People abandon them on our porch,
他们威胁如果我不接收他们
they threaten to euthanize them
就会对鹦鹉实行安乐死
if I don't take them.
现在我们的许多鹦鹉已经被领养过
Many of the birds that we have now have been adopted out
好多次又被送回来
numerous times, and they come back.
这是个大问题
It's a huge problem.
人们通常不理解
People don't always understand
如果一只鸟和你建立了联系
that when a bird forms a bond with you,
这种联系实际上是一种配偶联系
it's actually a mate bond.
它们不仅仅是你生活的一部分
They're not just part of your life,
它们就是你的生活
they become your life.
我基本不出去度假
I rarely go away on vacation --
它们实际上就是我的生活
they literally are my life.
人们会进来说
People will come in and they'll say,
我想要一只能说话并且很安静的鸟
"I want a bird that talks,that's quiet
还不咬人
and that doesn't bite,"
这种物种目前还没发现
and that species has not yet been discovered.
过来 过来
Come on over here!Come on! Come on!
过来
Come on over here!
鸟：锅来 锅来
BIRD: Come over here!Come over here!
-过来 -锅来
-Come on over here.-Come over here.
她最一开始的主人教会了她绝大数词汇
Her original owner taught her most of her vocabulary.
大家都爱亚马逊鹦鹉 因为它们能唱歌能说话
Everybody loves the Amazons cause they sing and they talk,
但咬人最凶的也是亚马逊鹦鹉
but nothing can bite you harder than an Amazon parrot.
上一秒你还在抱着它
One day you're cuddling it,
下一秒你脸就被咬掉了一块
and the next minute you're missing part of your face.
抓紧这些小鸟的脚
Squeeze those little birdie legs!
科娜：抓紧这些小鸟的--
KONA: Squeeze those little birdie --
抓紧这些小鸟的脚
Squeeze those little birdie legs!
抓紧
Squeeze!
咆哮吧 恐怖的鸟儿
Scary bird, roar!
科娜叫
[Kona roars]
科娜有着很大的词汇量
Kona, who has such a wonderful vocabulary
而且也特别讨喜 几乎所有人都想领养她
and is so animated and everybody wants to adopt her,
但她曾经咬下她主人的一块鼻子
actually removed this part of her owner's nose.
科娜[唱歌]：我爱你亲爱的宝贝
KONA [singing]:? I love you true dear
麦克劳德：一旦它们开始达到性成熟
McLEOD: Once they start to hit sexual maturity
它们的行为会发生巨大的变化
they have drastic behavioral changes.
你不会咬我的对吧
You're not gonna bite me right now are you?
上去吧
Up you go. Let's go, up up up.
好的
Oh, yeah, you are!
科娜：再见 再见
KONA: Goodbye! Goodbye!
麦克劳德：被鹦鹉咬伤后
McLEOD: Being injured by a parrot,
你不能对它生气
you can't be angry with them.
如果你让它们进入到你的生活中
If you take them into your life,
这是你得接受的事情之一
that's one of the things that you need to accept.
它们仍然是野生动物
It's still a wild animal.
旁白：不管是在笼子里还是翱翔在天空中
NARRATOR: In a cage or soaring above the canopy,
鹦鹉仍然是野生动物
parrots are still considered wild.
不像狗和猫
Unlike dogs and cats,
它们在近千年中
they haven't been domesticated
还没有被驯化
over thousands of years.
家养鹦鹉也只从野生鹦鹉中
Captive bred parrots are just a few generations
培养出了几代
from their wild cousins.
它们有着复杂的社会
They have complex social lives
和很大的大脑 就和灵长类动物一样
and large brains,like primates.
来自墨西哥州立大学的蒂姆赖特教授
Dr. Tim Wright from New Mexico State University
发现了
has discovered
鹦鹉们语言能力已经有了大幅度的提升
their language skills are remarkably advanced,
它们学习语言的方法和人类一样
and they learn to speak much as humans do.
赖特：学着和别人发出一样的声音
WRIGHT: Learning how to sound like others
似乎对鹦鹉来说非常重要
seems to be very important for these parrots.
如果你的声音听上去和其他鸟一样 那你就是它们的一员
If you sound like others, you're a member of their group.
鸟和鸟之间的联系非常紧密
They are very tightly bonded with each other.
在笼子里 它们在尝试着重新建立联系
Here in captivity, they're trying to recreate that bond
不管是谁在它们周围
with whoever's around.
旁白：赖特的调查显示
NARRATOR: Wright's research has revealed
它们能说方言
that they speak in regional dialects --
有些鹦鹉还是会两种预言
and some are even bilingual.
但是人类的插手
But human encroachment
让调查
is making it
变得越来越困难
increasingly difficult to study these birds.
黄颈亚马逊鹦鹉在野外生存环境不佳
Yellow-naped Amazons are not doing that well in the wild.
它们的数量大幅下降
There's been a very rapid decline.
旁白:鹦鹉通常在农场中单独的树上筑窝
NARRATOR: The parrots often nest in lone trees on ranches.
不幸的是 在这个地方繁育下一代非常有风险
Sadly, this is a risky place to raise their young.
赖特：它们没意识到
WRIGHT:They're not recognizing
来自新的捕食者人类的危险
the danger posed by these new human predators.
农场中的人经常偷猎这些鹦鹉
The ranch hands often will poach the parrots.
它们每天都会飞到外面去
They're out in the fields every day,
农场中的人每天都能看见这些鹦鹉知道它们在做些什么
they watch the parrots,they know what they're doing
并且知道鹦鹉的窝在哪
and have a good sense of where they're putting their nests,
也知道什么时候有小鹦鹉
and they know when there might be chicks there.
很显然小鹦鹉就在窝旁边
These birds are certainly touchy around their nest,
所以我们要保持距离
so we just try to keep our distance.
她要回来了 她正在回来
Oh yeah, she's going back,she's going back down now.
恩她正在进去 尾巴先进
Yeah, she's going in,tail first.
旁白：赖特研究了树洞
NARRATOR: Wright has been studying nest cavities
来了解鹦鹉父母们
in order to learn how parents
怎么教它们的孩子说话
teach language to their young.
赖特：好的 抓住
WRIGHT: Okay, hold it!
旁白：他试着把与这些鸟的接触
NARRATOR: He tries to keep his contact with the birds
做到最小化
to a minimum.
赖特：如果我们爬上树了
WRIGHT: If we do climb up,
那我们得动作快点早点离开
we do it quickly and get out of there.
哦 这个洞挺深
Oh, it's a deep one.
这有两个蛋
Ah, there are two eggs in there.
雌鸟会孵大概三周的蛋
The female will sit on these eggs for about three weeks
然后就会孵化出小鹦鹉
and then the chicks will hatch,
然后接下来的日子就很艰难了
and that's when the rough time comes.
很难说这些鹦鹉是否最后会留在家里
It's hard to say whether these chicks will be left in the nest
自由飞翔 或是成为宠物
and fly free, or become pets.
我曾尝试研究鹦鹉在巢里的行为
I've been trying to study their nesting behavior,
但是研究没法进行下去
and I can't do that
如果有人要把小鹦鹉从巢里带走
if people are taking the chicks
out of the nest,
这对于我来说是双倍的
so it's -- it's sort of a double, uh,
双倍的心痛
a double heart break for me.
我们当时正在一个夜间栖息地
We were visiting a night roost
记录那里的声音
to record the vocalizations there,
然后我就听到了一阵奇怪的声音
and I heard a strange sound.
嗨
Hola!
声音不太像是人类发出的
It wasn't quite human,
有什么再说 hello（英语你好）或者是hola(西班牙语嗨）
someone was saying "hello," or "hola."
赖特：打扰了
WRIGHT: Permisso!
洛瑞塔说话
[Lorita talks back]
赖特：实际上是一只鹦鹉在说话
WRIGHT:In fact, it was a parrot.
瞧瞧你
Look at you!
嗨
Hi!
你是一只黄颈亚马逊鹦鹉
You are a yellow-naped Amazon.
我和农场负责人聊天
I talked with the manager of the ranch,
他告诉我了一点鹦鹉的故事
and he told me a little bit about her history.
负责人在说西班牙语
[Manager speaking Spanish]
赖特：他们已经养了9个月的鹦鹉了
WRIGHT: So, they've had it about 9 months,
今年在鹦鹉还是小鸟的时候从窝里拿出来
it's a -- it was a chick taken from the nest this year,
从稍微南边一点的窝里拿出来的
um, from a nest a little bit south.
负责人在说西班牙语
[Manager speaking Spanish]
赖特：他说你只用爬上树
WRIGHT: He said, you just have to climb up the tree
然后手伸进去就可以拿到了
and stick your hand in and take it out.
西班牙语
[Speaking Spanish]
我问他像这样的小鸟能卖多少钱
I asked how much a chick like this would sell for,
然后他说 像这样的小鸟
and he said, well,when they're very young,
刚刚离开鸟巢的 可以大概卖到30或40美元
just out of the nest, they might sell for $30 or $40.
年龄稍微大一点的鸟
A bird that was a little bit older
并且和洛瑞塔一样健康的
and in good health like Lorita
可以卖到100美元
would sell for about $100.
她已经学会了很多的人类语言 西班牙语
She has learned a lot of human language words, Spanish words.
她会像人类那样笑 她会说hello或者是hola
She laughs, she calls "hello" or "hola,"
但是如果附近有其他鹦鹉
but when there are other parrots in the area,
她也会呼唤它们
she'll also call to them.
通常 一只鹦鹉
Normally, one parrot
会飞过去并加入它们
might fly over and join the flock.
但是洛瑞塔却办不到
But Lorita can't do that.
因为她在笼子里
She's in a cage.
洛瑞塔在叫
[Lorita squawking]
旁白：像洛瑞塔这样的小鹦鹉
NARRATOR:Baby parrots like Lorita
近千年中都是在鸟巢里长大
have been taken from the nest for thousands of years.
但是今天 三分之一的野生鹦鹉有生命危险
But today, nearly one third of wild parrots are endangered.
外国鸟儿的非法贩卖
The illicit trade in exotic birds
已经变成了数百万美元的生意
has become a multi-billion dollar business.
在1992年
In 1992,
美国禁止了
the U.S. banned
野生鸟类的进口
the importation of wild birds.
但是也是从那时起
But before then,
野生的鹦鹉
it was wild parrots
出现在我们的宠物店里
that filled our pet stores.
对于很多鹦鹉来说 这是它们生活开始的地方
For many parrots, this is how life began.
杰米金泰尔在1975年开了一家宠物商店
Jimmy Gentile opened his pet shop in 1975.
金泰尔：我们特殊在我们在卖
GENTILE: We kind of specialize in what I call
“不是宠物”的宠物
"no pets allowed" pets,
或者是特殊的陪伴动物--我们不卖狗和猫
or unique companion animals -- we don't do dogs or cats.
莉兹哈特曼80年代搬到了波士顿
NARRATOR: Liz Hartman moved to Boston in the '80s
上兽医学校
to attend vet school.
哈特曼：我在杰米的宠物店做兼职
HARTMAN: I worked part-time for Jimmy at the pet shop,
其实就是清理笼子
I really was just a cage cleaner.
当时有一只鸟 黄颈亚马逊鹦鹉
There was a bird there, a yellow-naped Amazon,
我当时觉得它太酷了
that I thought was so cool.
我想：“天呐我真的想把这只鸟带回家
I thought, "Oh, man, I really want to take this bird home,
我真的很想拥有它。”杰米说
I really want to own it." And Jimmy said,
“你应该养一只小鸟然后手把手的喂它
"You really should get a baby and hand feed it,
因为这是你与它建立感情联系的方式
because that's how you bond with them."
金泰尔：我订了一群小鸟
GENTILE: I had ordered a bunch of baby birds,
这些小鸟来自洪都拉斯
taken from the nest in Honduras.
有一天他们给我打电话告诉我说
A day came when they called me and they said,
“你的小鸟们到了”
"Your chicks are available."
所以我去机场拿那些盒子
So, I went to the airport, picked up the box.
哈特曼：我太激动了
HARTMAN: I was so excited,
我等不及有点忘乎所以了都
I couldn't wait,I was beside myself.
我把小鸟包好把它带回家
I packed up that bird and went home with it.
罗斯：当她把鹦鹉带回来的时候我记得
Russ: When she brought him home, I remember.
我们讨论过要不要养它 一开始
We had discussed it,and at first
我完全反对养鹦鹉
I was totally against it,
因为我知道鹦鹉能活多久
because I knew how long parrots lasted.
他完全赞成 他觉得太棒了
He was totally into it,he thought it was great.
我曾在宠物店工作过 一开始还是一团糟
They're messy, I've been in the pet stores.
一开始你必须用毛巾包着它
In the beginning you had to wrap him up in a towel,
因为他会想咬你
cause he would try to bite you.
这是我们第一次做父母的经历
It was our first experience at parenthood.
罗斯：我最终同意养他
RUSS: I eventually warmed up to the idea,
而我们经常忍不住坐那就看着他
and we couldn't help but sit there and just look at him,
看着这种野生鸟类出现在我们家里 实在是太神奇了
it was so amazing to see this wild bird in our house.
旁白：巴斯尔在家的头几年没出什么问题
NARRATOR: Basil's early years were trouble-free.
年轻的莉兹：早上好 巴斯尔
YOUNG LIZ: Good morning, Basil.
莉兹：头四年很美好很开心
LIZ: The first four years were lovely and blissful.
我早上起床后
I would come down in the morning
打开巴斯尔的笼子
and open Basil's cage.
不管我们何时在家 他基本上可以在地上自由的爬
Whenever we were home, he was basically free to crawl around,
他大部分时候都呆在笼子里
and he mostly stayed on his cage.
罗斯：他迅速学会了捡东西
RUSS: The quickness at which he could pick up anything,
他太神奇了
he was so amazing.
我觉得他有一种小聪明
I think he was wicked smart.
他喜欢和人交流
He loved the interaction.
[年轻的罗斯和巴斯尔在模仿爆炸声
[Young Russ and Basil
imitating explosion]
我们觉得：“我们会爱这只鸟爱到我们死去，
We thought, "We're gonna love this bird to death,
为了它余下的日子能够开心
and we're going to do whatever we need to do
我们愿意奉献一切
to make this bird happy for the rest of it's life."
旁白：鹦鹉通常只与一个人建立联系
NARRATOR: Parrots usually bond with one person.
对于巴斯尔来说 那个人是罗斯
For Basil,that person was Russ.
莉兹：它特别依赖罗斯
LIZ: He was so bonded to Russ.
罗斯经常出国出差
Russ traveled overseas a lot for business,
有时候他会离开一个月
and he'd been gone for about a month.
巴斯尔：嗨！
BASIL: Hi!
年轻的莉兹：你肯定很累了
YOUNG LIZ: You must be exhausted.
莉兹：他晚上回家然后直接睡觉
LIZ: He got home at night and we went to bed.
年轻莉兹：晚安巴斯尔
YOUNG LIZ: Good night, Basil.
莉兹：所有事情看上去都没问题
LIZ:Everything seemed fine.
我们第二天早上起来
We woke up the next morning
然后..
and...
你好
Hello!
巴斯尔把它胸前所有的羽毛都拔光了
Basil had plucked all of the feathers off of his chest.
巴斯尔叫
[Basil squawking]
就是把羽毛都拔光了
Like, just plucked it bald.
他以前从没拔过 从来没有
He'd never plucked before, ever.
这对我们来说打击非常大 因为我们
It was devastating to us because we didn't know
不知道发生了什么
what was going on.
我们后来觉得他是因为太生气了
We later determined he was so angry
以至于他愿意忍受这种痛苦
that he was willing to go through the pain
把他身上的羽毛拔掉
of pulling his own feathers out.
莉兹：这次没有伤到皮肤 只是露出了灰色的皮肤
LIZ: It wasn't down to the skin, but just the grey down.
我是说它肯定对
I mean, there had to be
他的回家有一种情感回馈
some sort of emotional response to Russ coming home.
我觉得他在表达自己的观点
I think he was making a point.
你必须陪伴着它们
You have to be there for them.
它们是社会动物
They are social animals.
这是我遇到最复杂的情况
I can't even imagine anything more complex.
它们就像灵长动物和人类一样
They're up there with the apes and the humans.
旁白：如果巴斯尔仍然在野外中
NARRATOR: If Basil was still in the wild,
他应该已经找到伴侣了
he would already have found a mate by now.
他和他的伴侣几乎不分开
They'd rarely be apart.
它们会养育下一代
Their mated bond would nurture the next generation,
确保种族的延续
ensuring the survival of the species.
一只野生的鹦鹉
A wild parrot
是很少单独呆着的
is seldom alone.
即使在飞行中
Even in flight,
一对鹦鹉很少会离得很远
a mated pair is almost never out of earshot.
对于一只野生鹦鹉来说
For a wild parrot,
很少形单影只
solitude is rare.
在波士顿郊区 一只鹦鹉被抛弃了
In a Boston suburb, a parrot has been left behind.
女：这个家庭失去了房子 银行没收了财产
WOMAN: The family lost the home, the bank had taken possession,
我接到电话
and I received a call.
卢叫
[Lou squawks]
这只鸟被丢弃了
The bird had been left behind
大概四天了
for approximately four days.
四天了
It was four days
还没见到有人进出那栋房子
since anyone had been last seen coming or going from the home.
房子里有水
It did have water,
但却没有鸟食
it did not have bird food available,
有其他宠物的食物
there was other pet food in the home.
把它们留在笼子里
To just be left behind in a cage,
这肯定对它们有影响--它们又不笨
it has to affect them --they're not stupid.
我曾听说过这种动物的故事
I've heard the stories that these animals go through
对于我来说很令我心痛
and for me it's utter heartbreak.
你之前给我打过电话么?
Did you give me a call earlier?
我打过 我已经三四天没见人在家了
I did, it's been three or four days since I've seen anyone here
我还听见鸟叫
and I've heard some bird noises.
好吧 我要去看看有什么
Okay, I'm gonna go take a look and see if I see anything.
伙计们我不能 如果你们不介意的话
Guys I can't, I just need you to stay outside
在外面等着我吧
if you don't mind for now.
叫声
[Squawking]
男：谢谢丽萨
MAN: Thanks, Lisa.
男：雨伞凤头鹦鹉 我们最喜欢的种类
MAN: Ah, an umbrella cockatoo, our favorite species.
我们只在房间里发现了这种动物
This is the only animal we found in the house.
哇 嗨
Aw, hey.
卡莉缇：麦克， 你能替我们照顾它吧？
CULLITY: So, you can
take care of him for us, Marc?
-谢谢-当然 没问题
-Thank you.-Sure, no problem.
-谢谢-拜拜 小家伙
-Thanks.-Bye, little guy!
男：在我们对鸟的评估过程中
MAN: Part of the evaluation process when we get a bird,
如果我们不知道他的名字 我们通常等他告诉我们
if we don't know his name, we wait for him to tell us.
他会说你好 然后说他的名字
He'll say hello, and then usually say his name.
这只鸟却从来没告诉过我们
In this case the bird never told us.
所有我们就用我们的一个好朋友给他取了名 卢
So, we just named him after a good friend of ours, Lou.
他似乎见到我就很紧张 也许对你会好点
He seems really nervous with me, maybe he'll be better with you,
想把他拿出来么?
wanna get him out?
旁白：麦克约翰逊和凯伦温莎
NARRATOR: Marc Johnson and Karen Windsor
致力于
have devoted their lives
拯救鹦鹉
to rescuing parrots.
温莎：每只鸟都有一个故事
WINDSOR:Every bird has a story.
每只鸟都有一段历史
Every bird has a history,
特别是令人伤感的历史
especially an emotional history.
它们带着它们的包袱
They carry their baggage.
我觉得大概很多黑暗角落里还有许多
I think there are probably a lot of forgotten birds
被人遗忘的鹦鹉
in a lot of dark corners of the world.
嗨嗨嗨
Hey, hi. Hi.
现在经济情况不好
It's hard economic times
我们的动物有时候却为此付出了代价
and our animals sometimes pay the price.
女：我上个星期跟您打过电话
WOMAN: I spoke to you on the phone last week
和您提过把我的鹦鹉麦克斯送去收养
about putting my parrot, Max,up for adoption,
他会有十年
he will be ten years...
男；朋友们 谁愿意收留它们
MAN: ...friends who could not keep them.
蓝金色相间的那只非常有攻击性
The blue and gold is very aggressive...
女：因为离婚我不得不
WOMAN: and due to a divorce I am being forced
搬进一座不让养鹦鹉的公寓里
to move into an apartment which will not allow...
男：我一直在联系兽医
MAN: I've been in contact with the vet
我打算对它进行安乐死如果没有
and I'm planning on euthanasia if there is no...
约翰逊：每天我们都收到邮件
JOHNSON:Everyday we get e-mails,
这是我们现在生活中最困难的一部分了
and that's the hardest part of our life now.
我们得拒绝大部分人
We have to say no a lot.
女：我想确定的是
WOMAN:...as I want to make sure
它们不会受苦或者被虐待
they don't end up suffering or being mistreated...
女：它快把我丈夫和孩子逼疯了
WOMAN: ...she's driving my husband and children crazy...
男：我不能再这么生活下去了
MAN: I cannot live like this anymore,
期待收到您的回信
I hope to hear from you.
旁白：约翰逊近几年目睹了鹦鹉
NARRATOR: Johnson has witnessed the proliferation of parrots
的泛滥
over the years.
故事由一则售鸟广告开始
It all began with a want ad.
约翰逊：在80年代我有间小的陶器工作室
JOHNSON: In the 1980s I had a small pottery studio.
我非常迷恋雨林
I had a deep admiration for the rainforest
所以我想要一只宠物
and I wanted to get a pet,
而我觉得有一只奇怪的动物会很好玩
AND I thought something exotic would be fun,
所以我在二手市场上花900美元买了一只鹦鹉
so I bought a parrot in the Want advertiser for $900.
沃利是一只蓝黄相间的金刚鹦鹉
Wally was a blue and gold macaw.
他是只很棒的鸟
He was a wonderful bird.
人们进到店里来看见我有一只鹦鹉会说
People would come in and see I had a parrot and they would say,
“哇 我有个堂兄也有一只鹦鹉。”
"Oh, I have a cousin that's got one of those,"
“我兄弟有一只。”
"My brother's got one of those,"
“我也有一只鹦鹉 我不想要了
"I've got one of those that I don't want anymore,
你想要么？”
would you like my parrot?"
我当时并没意识到问题有多严重
Not knowing how big the problem was,
我觉得 挺好的啊 因为人们给我的鹦鹉
I thought, well, this is great, because people were
值不少钱呢
giving parrots that were worth lots of money.
我们当时被鹦鹉包围了
We were being besieged by birds.
当我意识到问题的严重性时我已经有了30只鹦鹉了 每天还有人送来新的
Before I knew it I had 30 of them with more coming every day.
原来人们给我鹦鹉是因为
It turns out, people were giving me their parrots
它们是一种非常难养的宠物
because they're very difficult pets.
而我是镇里唯一愿意养的
And I was the only game in town.
没人愿意领养这些没人要的鸟
Nobody else would take unwanted birds,
所以人们来找我
so people came to visit me.
在我意识到之前 鹦鹉已经多到陶器工作室呆不下了
Before I knew it I had outgrown the pottery studio,
所以我得找出方法解决它
and I had to figure out some way of dealing with it.
旁白：约翰逊关闭了工作室
NARRATOR:Johnson closed the studio
并搬到了郊区的房子里
and moved to a house in the suburbs.
约翰逊：从那时起
JOHNSON: From that point on
房子建好了又有人把鹦鹉送过来
it was, if you build it they will come.
房子里到处都是鹦鹉
The birds took over the house.
每个房间里都有五六只鹦鹉
Every single room had half a dozen birds in it.
食品储藏室 空房间 卧室
The pantry, the spare rooms, the bedrooms.
温莎：当我第一次来做志愿者时
WINDSOR: When I first came to volunteer,
我发现鹦鹉在厨房里
I found parrots in the kitchen,
客厅里 卧室里
parrots in the living room, parrots in the bathroom.
约翰逊：没过多久我们就有了300多只鹦鹉
JOHNSON: Within no time we had over 300 parrots.
旁白：这个房子已经变成了鸟类保护所
NARRATOR: The house had become a sanctuary.
每天都有收养请求
With more requests each day,
约翰逊逃跑了--第二次
Johnson ran out of space --again.
公鸡叫
[Rooster crowing]
约翰逊：幸运的是
JOHNSON: As luck would have it,
我们遇到了一所废弃的养鸡场
we came across this abandoned chicken farm.
我无意中发现这个地方
I kind of stumbled on this place by accident.
虽然很破烂但我觉得这就是我们一直在找的
It's a wreck but I think it's what we've been waiting for.
温莎：我们会有大量的工作
WINDSOR: This is gonna be an enormous amount of work.
特别多
It's too much.
约翰逊：这事吓到凯伦了
JOHNSON: It scared the hell out of Karen,
但是我却看到了一个非常好的机会
but I saw it as a golden opportunity.
旁白：在两年内
NARRATOR: Within two years,
他们把保护所扩大了三倍
they had tripled the size of the sanctuary.
但是过了不久 即使是新的设备
But in no time, even the new facility
都因承受不了而损坏
would be bursting at the seams.
这些没人要的鹦鹉是从哪来的?
Where were all these unwanted parrots coming from?
它们来自美洲 非洲 亚洲印尼
From South America, Africa, Asia, Indonesia,
来自野外
parrots were streaming in from the wild.
当美国禁止引进野生鸟类时
When it became illegal to import wild birds to the U.S.,
人工培育填补了空白
domestic breeding filled the void.
今天饲养鹦鹉
Today, the practice of breeding parrots
很有争议
is not without controversy.
女：人们可以花40美元
WOMAN: Anybody with $40
在宠物商店买一只鹦鹉
can walk into any Petco and buy a parrot.
没有规章管理
There are no regulations.
你想要多少就可以有多少
Anybody can have as many of them as they want,
人们可以饲养它 也可以贩卖它
they can breed them, they can sell them.
我没资格评论 因为我也这么做过
I'm not one to talk, because I did it.
各位 请用手喂
Hand feed everybody.
很久以前
This was a long time ago,
还没有鸟类保护所之类的东西
there wasn't any such thing as a rescue or a sanctuary,
因为不需要
there was no need for it.
旁白：菲比和哈里林登
NARRATOR: Phoebe and Harry Linden
曾经是非常受人尊敬的饲养者
were once highly respected breeders.
40年前
It all started nearly 40 years ago.
哈里:1971 我在报纸上
HARRY: In 1971,I saw in the paper
看见广告 有人想卖鹦鹉
somebody was advertising they had to get rid of a parrot.
我基本上从那个人手中把鹦鹉救了下来
And I basically rescued him from this guy.
然后我发现
And then I started finding out
他们的鸟是从野外捉的
that they were bringing in birds from the wild.
你可以用钱买到
You could go down and you could buy at wholesale price
你想要的任何鸟
just about any bird you'd want.
我有了一只鹦鹉 另一只鹦鹉
I got another parrot, and another parrot.
在你们知道前
Before you knew it,
我们已经有了很多的鹦鹉了
we had so many birds in the house
我们不能再住在那个房子里了 我必须重新找个房子
we couldn't live there anymore, I had to get another house.
旁白：40年前
NARRATOR: 40 years ago,
如果你购买一只鹦鹉
if you purchased a parrot,
基本可以肯定，这只鹦鹉来自野外
it would almost certainly be a parrot from the wild.
捕捉和运输
Capture and transport
产生了可怕的后果
took a terrible toll.
据估计
It's been estimated
大概有超过70%的被抓住的野生鹦鹉
that more than 70% of wild-caught parrots
在到达宠物店前就死了
died before ever reaching the pet store.
哈里：我对这些被抓的野生鹦鹉很同情
HARRY: I felt bad about these wild caught parrots,
然后我想 如果我来饲养繁殖这些鹦鹉
and I thought, if we bred these birds,
那么人么就不用去抓野生鹦鹉了
then people would not need to pull them out of the wild.
我把这个生意命名为圣巴巴拉鸟类农场
I named the business Santa Barbara Bird Farm.
菲比：当我们开始培育鹦鹉时
PHOEBE: When we started to breed parrots,
我辞去工作 手把手的养这些鸟
I quit my job and just hand-fed birds.
哈里和我决定不生小孩
Harry and I decided not to have human children,
我发现我会把我的爱心
and I just found that I could like zip open my heart
倾注到这些小鸟身上
and pour it into these baby birds.
我们想要留住每一只鸟
HARRY: We wanted to keep every single one of them.
旁白：林登有着很高的名声
NARRATOR: The Linden's had an excellent reputation
和很长的等待批准的名单
and a long waiting list.
他们手把手的饲养鹦鹉
They were hands-on with the chicks,
精心挑选合适的购买者
and carefully screened potential buyers.
但是在70年代末 事情发生了变化
But in the late '70s the landscape began to change.
一个名叫巴雷塔的电视剧
A TV series came out called "Baretta."
剧中的侦探有一只中等大小的葵花风头鹦鹉
This detective had a medium
sulfur-crested cockatoo
这让鹦鹉成为了最炫的宠物
that made it look like the coolest pet you could have,
它们不会尖叫 不会拔自己的羽毛
they don't scream, they don't pick their feathers,
它们对你言听计从
they do what you tell them to do.
去窗户前看看
Go look in that window
有多少人因为它走不动路
and tell me if somebody's getting stabbed.
菲比：人们开始认为鹦鹉特别有魅力
PHOEBE: The word got out there, how charming,
特别友善
how companionable parrots were.
电话开始响个不停
The phone started ringing off the wall.
领养申请一夜之间增多
Demand bloomed overnight.
突然之间你得到鹦鹉变得特别容易
All of a sudden,you could get one anywhere.
一开始事情不是这样的
In the beginning it wasn't like that.
我们开始听说
We started to hear about
拯救和保护鹦鹉之类的
rescues and sanctuaries.
我们开始意识到
And we started to realize that,
哇 有好多没人要的鹦鹉
wow, there are unwanted parrots.
我们也预测到将会有
When we saw that there was going to be
相当多的没人要的鹦鹉
a tremendous amount of fallout from that,
我们决定停止繁殖
we decided to stop breeding.
我们永远不会再繁殖鹦鹉
We shut breeding down forever.
旁白：林登夫妇决定结束这项生意
NARRATOR: The Linden's decided to close the business
相反 开始关注于为
and instead focus on building
他们当时拥有的鹦鹉来说最好的家
the best facility they could for the birds they still had.
哈里：这个鸟类饲养场
HARRY: This new aviary
可能会在树或者草中
can actually have foraging potential
藏着真正适合鸟类的食物
with the trees and the grass.
菲比：我们现在
PHOEBE: We're in the position now
想收回那些我们曾经养过的
where we want to take back
现在需要一个家的鹦鹉
any baby who we raised who needs a home.
让它们
So, they get to live a life
能够自己做决定 锻炼
where they can make their own decisions, exercise,
有新鲜空气 新鲜食物
have access to fresh air, fresh food.
哈里：很多像我们一样的饲养者已经停止培育鹦鹉
HARRY: A lot of breeders like ourselves just stopped breeding,
但我们有很多鹦鹉仍然在外面受苦
but we still have some of the parrot mills out there
仍然每年生很多小鸟
that produce a lot of babies every year,
以后也会有鹦鹉
and so there's still going to be parrots out there
会有各种麻烦
who are gonna run into problems in the future
会被送去领养
and have to be put up for adoption.
菲比：真正关心鹦鹉的人
PHOEBE: People who really care about parrots
不会买鹦鹉--他们会领养
don't buy birds --they adopt.
我们需要尽我们所能
We need to take care of the parrots who are here,
好好照顾在这里的鹦鹉
the best way that we can,
并关心野外的鹦鹉
and conserve the parrots in the wild.
旁白：拯救鹦鹉的矛盾之处在于
NARRATOR: It is the paradox of the parrot.
随着野生数量的减少
As numbers dwindle in the wild,
在笼子里被救助的鸟却
the number of rescues in captivity
越来越多
continues to increase.
随着保护所的生活越来越艰难
With sanctuaries struggling to stay afloat,
那些没人要的鹦鹉命运
the fate of unwanted parrots
一天天变得更加重要
is becoming more precarious every day.
女:继父死后
WOMAN: The step-father died,
养女给我们打电话让我们收养费根
and the daughter called up and asked us to take Fagan.
-你好？嗨
-Hello? -Hey.
-这就是他-好的谢谢你
-Here he is. -Okay, thank you.
好的 谢谢你
'Kay, thank you.
旁白：在底特律郊区
NARRATOR: In a Detroit suburb,
一只名叫费根的鹦鹉遇到了玛丽克罗利
a parrot named Fagan has found his way to Marie Crowley.
好孩子好孩子
Good boy, good boy.
克罗利：当我从笼子里把费根拿出来的时候
CROWLEY: When I took Fagan out of the carrier,
很明显可以看出
it was pretty obvious that he had
他腹部有他自虐的伤
a big self-mutilation wound on his abdomen.
你是真的想把自己吃了 对吧小家伙
You really chewed yourself up buddy, huh?
我注意到它身上有很浓的尼古丁味
I noticed that he smelled heavily of nicotine.
你臭臭
You smell, you stink.
很明显他很长时间没洗澡了
He obviously hadn't been bathed in a long time.
他们抽烟把 哈?
Did they smoke, hmm?
他身上有一层粘糊糊的东西
He was just covered in goop.
你这只小脏鸟
You are a dirty, dirty bird.
需要洗澡啦
Need a bath.
走吧
There you go.
我注意到我的手也很恶心
I noticed my hands were just disgusting.
手上全是尼古丁
They were covered in nicotine,
两天以后才好
my hands were stained for two days after.
我抓住你啦 走吧
I gotcha, there you go.
坏生活结束喽
It's all done.
[Purrs]
对头 坏生活结束啦 走吧
Yes, the yuckies are over, there you go.
我知道他之前的生活环境
I knew that the conditions that he was coming from
非常非常差
were really, really poor.
好孩子 嘘
Good boy. Shh.
旁白：在充满烟味的房子生活
NARRATOR: After living in a smoke-filled house
近25年后
for nearly 25 years,
费根是欧罗斯医生一个挑战
Fagan presented a challenge for Dr. Orosz.
女：让我听听它的胸腔 让我听听好么？
WOMAN: Let's listen to the chest, can you let me listen?
欧罗斯：当费根进来的时候
OROSZ: When Fagan walked through the door,
我看见的是一只很惨的鸟
I saw a bird in crisis.
他的羽毛因为尼古丁而油油的
His feathers were greasy with nicotine.
它有一大块没毛的地方
He had a large patch
是它在胸前自虐
where he had been mutilating on his chest.
它简直就是一团糟
He was basically a mess.
-在它喉咙后部 看到了么-恩
-Back of his throat, see that? -Ah, okay, mm-hmm.
它以前的女主人老是抽烟对吧？
He's from a home where the lady smoked all the time, right?
是那些廉价商店的雪茄
It was those little dime-store cigars.
呵呵
Oh, great.
克罗利：很明显他身体上已经对
CROWLEY: It became pretty clear that he was actually
尼古丁成瘾了
physically addicted to the nicotine.
他开始有痉挛
He started having seizures.
我们必须帮他戒除尼古丁
We had to detox him from the nicotine,
而且他身上有这么一大片
and then he had this large area
他自虐过的地方
where he's been mutilating his body.
这些事情很难
Those are very difficult things
让这只鸟恢复 很难
to overcome in birds, very difficult.
和精神科医生讨论过后
In discussions with psychiatrists,
我觉得最接近的说法是
the closest thing I can think of
类似于皮肤反应的东西
is that it could be something like cutting.
当它们自虐时
When they do physical damage to themselves,
这是一种释放机制
it's a kind of a release effect.
我们必须帮助它减少压力
We had to help him with his stress.
伙计 把这个领子穿上怎么样
Here, buddy, come put this collar on, okay?
好样的
Good job.
克罗利：费根已经戴了很久的领子了
CROWLEY: Fagan has been in a collar so long
他很适应戴领子
that he is okay with putting a collar on,
他不是特别反对反抗戴领子
he doesn't really argue or fight about it.
费根特别营养不良
Fagan was really malnourished his whole life.
我们花了好几个星期才让他吃喝正常
It took weeks to get him to eat properly.
在密西根没有
There are no sanctuaries
鹦鹉保护所
for parrots in Michigan,
只有像我一样的人
there's just some people like me
竭尽所能拯救鹦鹉
who try and take them in as best they can.
它们无处可去
They don't have anywhere else to go,
所以只有来这个郊区社区
so they end up in this little suburbia neighborhood
你不会想到能在这见到鹦鹉--我的地下室
where you'd never expect to see a parrot -- in my basement!
鸟叫
[Birds squawking]
我有26只鹦鹉
I have 26 birds here.
这个地方不甚理想
The situation is less than ideal.
但我们已经做到了最好--我们装上了空气过滤器
But we do everything we can -- we've put up air filters,
全光谱照明 我还在这放了棕榈树
full-spectrum lighting, and then I keep palm trees down there
因为我发现如果有棕榈树的话
'cause I figure if the palm trees stay alive,
就不用那么多的光了
then the lighting is at least adequate.
每只鸟每天都需要喂食喂水
Every bird here has to be fed and watered
三四次 它们的笼子需要打扫
three to four times a day, their cages have to be cleaned.
这是爱的工作
It's a labor of love.
旁白：和大多数拯救鹦鹉的人一样
NARRATOR: Like most parrot rescues,
克罗利是不收钱的 密西根的 鸟类的朋友
Crowley's non-profit, Feathered Friends of Michigan,
仅够勉强维持生活
barely scrapes by.
美国的大多数保护所和救助站
Most sanctuaries and rescues
都已经满了
across the United States are full,
所以我们只能
so we all make do
在坏的环境中竭尽所能做到最好
with the bad situation as best we can.
过来 过来 我来把你领子取下来哈？
Come here. Come here. Let's take your collar off, huh?
对于费根来能每天有时间
It's important Fagan gets some time
把领子取下来很重要
out of his collar every day,
这样他就可以用嘴整理羽毛
so that he can work on preening his feathers
也可以拍拍翅膀 爬爬行
and flapping his wings and climbing.
它戴了很长时间的领子了 他有点不开心
He's been in a collar so long, he falls a lot.
因为他不能打开翅膀控制平衡
Because he can't open his wings to catch himself
就像普通鸟那样
like a bird should.
所以我们要帮他恢复这部分的肌肉
So, we're gonna work on building those muscles back up over time.
你想跳舞么？ 想么？
Would you like to dance? Yeah?
你想跳舞？[笑声]
You would like to dance? [Laughs]
[放瑞格舞曲]
[Playing reggae music]
我向天空抬起头
? My head up to the sky
哦啦啦 啦啦 啦啦
? Ooh, la la, la la, la la
我要一直对着天空抬着头
? I'm going to keep my head up
to the sky ?
我不能忽略生活
? Won't let life pass me by ?
因为我知道风雨过后
? 'Cause after the rain comes down ?
会有晴天
? The sun will always come back around ?
而我要对天空抬起头
? And I'm going to keep my head up to the sky ?
我们要读这个 这个长的
Yeah, we gotta read this one. This is a long one, man.
旁白：费根还不适应和其他鸟生活在一起
NARRATOR:Fagan isn't comfortable with other birds yet,
而且因为他的健康问题 玛丽需要
and with his health issues, Marie needs to keep
近距离观察
a close watch.
所以他和家庭成员生活在一起
So, he lives with the family.
克罗利：我儿子正在认颜色
CROWLEY: My son was learning his colors.
哪个是红色
What's red?
好样的费根
Good job, Fagan!
每当我们在复习一个颜色的时候
And whenever we went over a color,
费根就会抬起头然后用嘴碰一下那个颜色
Fagan would go up and tap it with his beak,
所以我们就给他
so, we brought these out and --
哪个是绿色
What's green?
他喜欢辨别颜色
He does like to differentiate between the colors.
真棒
Good.
而我要做的就是给他的大脑一种锻炼方式
What I'm trying to do is give his mind a way to exercise,
这是另一种治疗
it's another form of enrichment
已经被证实能够减少鹦鹉的焦虑
that's been shown to reduce anxiety in parrots.
哪个是黄色
What's yellow?
对于我来说和他接触是“非性的”
It's a non-sexual way for me to interact with him.
这样的能打破他想和我建立伴侣
That will kind of break the cycle
联系的循环
of the mated bond that he's trying to create with me.
如果费根在野外的话 他能有自己鸟群
If Fagan was in the wild, he would have a flock,
他能够找到一个伴侣 它们就可以爬到树洞里
he would find a mate and they'd crawl up into a tree cavity
建窝生孩子
and build a nest and have babies.
但是在笼子里
But in captivity,
会让想费根一样的很多鸟感到失意
that causes a lot of frustration for birds like Fagan.
哪个是红色 好样的
What's red? Good job!
好
Yeah.
哪个是黄色
What's yellow?
不幸的是 对于非洲灰鹦鹉来说
Unfortunately for the African Grey's,
它们的智力水平却
their intelligence level ended up being
让它们最终被关起来
somewhat their undoing in captivity.
男：这是什么玩具 艾利克斯：卡车
-MAN: What toy? -ALEX: Truck.
男：对拉-女：真聪明
-MAN: That's right! -WOMAN: Good birdie.
-这是什么？艾利克斯：钥匙串
-What is it? -ALEX: Key chain.
真聪明
Good boy!
旁白：90年代 艾利克斯向世界展示了
NARRATOR: In the '90s, Alex showed the world
鹦鹉能做的不止是学人说话
that parrots are capable of more than just mimicking.
-女；这是什么玩具？艾利克斯：钉子
-WOMAN: What toy? -ALEX: Nail.
旁白：艾琳佩珀伯格所培训的艾利克斯在大家心里种下了种子
NARRATOR: Irene Pepperberg's work with Alex was seminal.
佩珀伯格:告诉我这是什么颜色？
PEPPERBERG: Tell me what color, what color?
艾利克斯：黄色 -黄色 对啦
-ALEX: Yellow. -Yellow, that's right.
克罗利：当培训好的艾利克斯出来时
CROWLEY: When the work with Alex came out,
每个人都想要一只艾利克斯
everybody wanted to buy an Alex.
一下有好多人在养这种鸟
The breeding of them skyrocketed.
但是艾利克斯并不是非洲灰鹦鹉的常态
But Alex isn't your everyday African Grey,
他需要经过长年的训练
he's a bird that was trained for hours a day for years on end.
大多数非洲鹦鹉不会说话
Most African Greys don't talk.
它们喜欢发出令人讨厌的微波炉声音呢
They mostly love to make really obnoxious microwave sounds,
手机的声音
and phone sounds --
类似这样人们听了会不舒服的声音
stuff that people find hard on their ears.
所以它们中的大部分都死了
So, they end up getting surrendered a lot.
我觉得只要艾利克斯还在YouTube的排行榜上靠前
I think as long as Alex is at the top of the YouTube charts,
他会在我的牺牲名单上也排在前面
he's gonna be at the top of my surrender charts.
旁白：在野外 费根的智慧
NARRATOR: In the wild, Fagan's intelligence
能够有用
would be put to task.
在飞行中 他的大脑
In flight, his large brain
能够计算空间 风和速度
would measure space, wind and speed.
他可以计算距离和食物的来源
He'd calculate distance and sources of food.
如果遇到危险 他可以打架
If confronted, he'd take flight.
这些野外的直觉还是十分完美
These wild instincts are still very much intact
特别是对于像巴斯尔这样的鸟来说
for birds like Basil.
头四年 像我说的 非常美好
The first four years, like I said, were wonderful.
亲亲
Kiss kiss!
他很甜他很平易近人很可爱
He was sweet, he was handleable, he was lovely,
但是他青春期后来来了
and then adolescence set in.
他变得越来越有攻击性
He just became progressively more aggressive.
我会在周日早上坐在餐厅里
I'd be sitting at the dinning room table Sunday morning
读报纸
reading the paper,
他会追着我
and he would seek me out.
这让我意识到
It got to the point
我不能再把笼子随便打开了
where I could not leave the cage open at all.
如果我在房间里而笼子是开着的
If I were in the house and the cage was open,
他会立刻爬下笼子攻击我的脚
he would immediately climb down the cage to attack my feet.
他决定恨我
He just decided I was the person he hated.
他会啄她
He would lunge at her,
他会从笼子里飞出来戳她
he would fly out of the cage at her.
莉兹：有一天早上我起床 打开笼子门
LIZ: One morning I got up, I opened the door to his cage
然后我转过身去开窗
and then I turned around to open the window,
他就直直的向我飞来
and he just flew at me,
他挂了我的耳朵
he was hanging off my ear.
你是不会明白的 他可以一直很可爱很开心
You just didn't know, he could be all sweet and happy,
转身就咬你
turn around and bite you.
当我们有了孩子的时候 巴斯尔还没有准备
When we had the kids, Basil wasn't quite ready
迎接这些外来人
to have these foreigners.
我的孩子们也不懂
They didn't know any better,
他们觉得他们可以像我一样去看鹦鹉
they thought they could walk up just like I did.
莉兹：当时我女儿四岁了
LIZ: My daughter was four years old at the time
她当时在喂他
and she was feeding him
饼干 然后他抓了她
a cracker,and he nailed her.
尖叫
[Screaming]
我听见尖叫声下楼一看
I heard the screaming, I came running down the stairs.
很糟糕
It was awful.
罗斯：那时我们开始意识到
RUSS: That was when we started to realize that
可能巴斯尔并不会
perhaps Basil wasn't going to
对孩子好
warm up so much to the kids.
我觉得不能再把这个动物当成宠物了
I didn't think I could keep this animal as a pet anymore.
旁白：没人知道有多少只鹦鹉被关了起来
NARRATOR: No one knows the number of parrots in captivity.
据估计美国有1千万到4千万
Estimates range from 10 to 40 million in the U.S.
它们中很多生活在稳定的家庭里
While many live in stable homes,
每年有上千只死去
thousands are surrendered each year.
幸存下来的鸟怎么样了呢？
What happens to the parrots who fall through the cracks?
被抛弃在空房子里呆了四天后
Abandoned for four days in an empty house,
卢是幸存的鸟儿中比较幸运的
Lou is one of the lucky ones.
在鹦鹉之家 卢的新生活就要展开了
At Foster Parrots, Lou's next chapter is about to begin.
因为不知道他的过去
With no clues about his past,
为他提供怎样的照顾是一个挑战
providing the right care will be a challenge.
没人知道他有多大了 他呆过几个家庭
No one knows how old he is, how many homes he's had,
或者是他有没有见过其他鸟
or if he's ever seen anther parrot.
鸟叫
[Birds squawking]
像卢这样的鸟
How must it feel
第一次进到保护所
for a bird like Lou, entering a sanctuary
是什么心情
for the first time?
上千种叫声 因为有上百只鸟
Thousands of sounds, hundreds of birds,
每一只都在诉说自己的故事
each calling out with its own story.
鸟：嗨
BIRD: Hi.
小美鸟
Pretty bird.
温莎：当我们穿过设备房时
WINDSOR: When we walk through the facility,
很重要的是让每个人都意识到
it's important that everybody understand
他们所见的是一场灾难
that what they are seeing is a tragedy.
我们所见的
What we are looking at
是人类作为鹦鹉伴侣的
is the failure of humans as companions
失败
to parrots.
旁白：每个新来的都会进行全面体检
NARRATOR: Any new arrival gets a full physical.
这对没有药物治疗史的鸟来说特别重要
It's especially critical for a bird with no medical history,
比如卢
like Lou.
约翰逊：他被留在一个抛弃的房间里
JOHNSON: Was left in an abandoned home.
男：那有食物和水么？
MAN: Was there food and water?
有一袋狗粮
There was a bag of dog food.
狗粮？呵呵
Dog food? Nice.
可怜的卢 好的 小家伙
Poor Lou. Okay, buddy.
让我们看看你的翅膀
Let's look at your plumage, Lou.
看上去你过得不怎么样哈
Sounds like you had a tough life, huh?
鸟类兽医意识到
Any avian vet realizes that
圈养的鹦鹉有很大的
the stress our captive parrots are under
压力
is immense.
来吧
There you go.
对它这种物种来说体重不错
Pretty good weight for his species.
我们把这些鸟带回家剪断它们的翅膀
We take these birds into our homes and we cut their wings.
小家伙很害怕 心跳很快
This guy's pretty scared, his heart rate's off the chart.
大概一分钟跳300多下
Probably over 300 beats a minute.
我们把它关在笼子里
We house them in cages
我们不让它们和它们的同类在一起
and we don't allow them to be with their own species.
你可以想象下它们所承受的压力
You can imagine the stress on these animals.
卢疯狂的叫
[Lou squawking frantically]
旁白：压力会降低免疫系统
NARRATOR: Stress is known to lower the immune system.
被剪过的翅膀和笼子
Clipped wings and cages
确保了它们的牢狱生活 鸟类兽医
guarantee a sedentary life, and avian vets
发现心脏病
are finding that heart disease
对笼子里的鹦鹉来说非常普遍
is all too common in captive parrots,
特别是那些饮食不好的
especially those with poor diets.
鹦鹉也会有传染病
Parrots can also carry infectious diseases.
卢要有30天的检疫期
Lou will stay in quarantine for 30 days,
以确保他没有传染病
to make sure he's not contagious.
他的测试结果决定了他的未来
His test results will determine his future.
饲养着550多只鸟
With over 550 birds,
鹦鹉之家已远远超过其饲养能力
Foster Parrots is well beyond capacity.
约翰逊：如果我们再多领养一只鸟
JOHNSON: If we take another bird,
志愿者们会把我杀了的
my volunteers would kill me.
温莎：35名志愿者6名员工
WINDSOR: 35 volunteers and a staff of six.
我们人手还不够
That's not enough humans
照顾这些与人类有紧密联系的鸟类
to meet the needs of really human-bonded birds.
你在站上去么？ 乖
Are you gonna step up? Good girl.
温莎：我们不能把这些
WINDSOR: We cannot integrate
鹦鹉放回它们自己的社会中
these parrots with their own species.
它们也不适应人类社会
And yet they don't fit into a human society either.
我们该怎么处理这些鸟类呢？
What are we to do with these birds?
因为它们都意识不到它们是鸟类
'Cause they don't even know they're birds.
约翰逊：皮伯展示了一幅不正常的拔过羽毛的外形
JOHNSON: Peepers exhibits an unusual feather picking profile.
她把她头上和脖子上的羽毛
She pulls the feathers
用脚拔了
out of her head and neck with her foot,
让她现在长得像秃鹰
giving her that vulture-like appearance,
如果她知道
that if she only knew
她应该长什么样 她也许就不会经常这么做了
what she looked like, she might not do so often.
你仍然很漂亮
You're still beautiful.
作为一只家养的鹦鹉
Being a domestically raised bird,
她认得人
she identifies with humans
她也想做人类的伴侣
and she also wants to mate with humans.
这样不好皮伯
That's not good peepers.
你只是想被爱 这样错得很离谱么？
You just wants to be loved,is that so wrong?
我们接到一个女人的电话
We received a call from a woman
她的邻居在寒冬把皮伯
whose neighbor was keeping peepers in an unheated porch
放在没有暖气的走廊里
in the middle of winter.
你是个乖女孩
You're a good girl.
现在我们接收那些处于生死边缘的鸟
Right now we take in birds when it's a life and death situation.
我是说 你必须接收那些鸟
I mean, you have to take that bird in.
需要的照料工作太多了
The care requirements are so huge
你永远感觉不到你成功了
you can never feel like you've been successful.
温莎：这是给你的吗？
WINDSOR: Is that for you?
温莎：从我有沃利的第一天起
JOHNSON: From the very first day
那只蓝黄相间的金刚鹦鹉
I got Wally, the blue and gold macaw,
我就决定要让他的生活一天比一天好
my resolve was to make his life better, every day, and...
天呐 对不起
God, sorry...
给我两分钟
Give me a sec.
我是说 当有人问我
I mean, when people ask me
对于金刚鹦鹉来说合适的笼子大小
what is the right size cage for a macaw,
没有适合金刚鹦鹉的笼子
there is no right size cage for a macaw,
应该有35平方英里 是
it's 35 square miles, you know, it's like,
很大的 是天空 是
it's huge, and it's the sky, it's...
女：它的主人是一位老先生
WOMAN: The owner is an older gentleman
老先生的妻子四年前去世了
whose wife passed away about four years ago,
那只鸟一只啄自己
and the bird has been pecking away at himself...
男：嗨马克 我妈妈三个星期前去世了
MAN: Hey, Marc, my mother died three weeks ago
我得为一只风头鹦鹉找一个地方
and I need to find a place for a cockatoo...
女：给你写这封信让我痛不欲生
WOMAN: It's killing me writing to you like this
但我必须要为它找个新家
but I must find a new home...
约翰逊：当我一开始建起鹦鹉之家时
JOHNSON: When I first started Foster Parrots,
我觉得我会接受每一只需要家的鸟
I thought we could take every single bird that needed a home.
但是很明显 这样的数字太巨大了
But of course, the numbers were staggering,
大到我们每年要接到1000多个鹦鹉的收养
to a point now where we have over a thousand calls a year
申请
for surrender.
旁白：如果这些鹦鹉能够被放回野外
NARRATOR: How wonderful it would be if these parrots
该多么好啊
could be released to the wild.
但是它们应该没有在野外生存的技能
But it's unlikely they'd have the skills to survive
不像它们那些在野外的同类一样
like their wild cousins.
他们传播疾病的风险也特别大
And the risk of spreading disease would be too great.
因为数量特别少 每一只鹦鹉都很重要
With populations so low, every parrot matters.
在哥斯达黎加 一只绯红金刚鹦鹉正在呼唤他的母亲
In Costa Rica, a scarlet macaw is calling to his mother.
小鸟叫
[Baby bird squawking]
男：在杰弗里还在孵化的时候我就知道它很特别
MAN: I knew Geoffrey was special from hatch.
他的叫声很可爱
He had a very cute peep.
它们在孵化前
They communicate with mum
就和母亲交流
well before they've hatched.
所以 小鸟们实际上可以通过蛋壳
So, the babies will actually be talking to mum
和母亲说话
through the egg.
当孵化出来时 它们非常无助
They hatch open and they're so helpless,
它们全身都是湿的
they're all wet
还有脐带
and they still have the little umbilical cord
连着蛋上
attached to the egg.
我们不管它12个小时 让卵黄
We leave them about 12 hours, to allow the yolk
能够被用完
to be used up.
杰弗里孵出来了
So, little Geoffrey hatched out
他太可爱了
and he was just so cute.
我能从杰弗里孵化时看出来他很聪明
I could tell Geoffrey was a smart one from hatch.
旁白：ARA项目培育被救下来的金刚鹦鹉
NARRATOR: The ARA Project is breeding rescued macaws
旨在让它们的后代能被放回野外
in order to release their offspring to the wild.
它们的父母以前是宠物或者是被救下来的鹦鹉
The parents, who are former pets and rescued birds,
通常不太清楚怎么培育它们的孩子
don't always know how to raise their young.
卡斯尔斯：杰弗里的母亲原来是只宠物
CASTLES: Geoffrey's mother was an ex-pet,
他的父亲被人从野外偷猎过来
and his father was poached from the wild.
他的母亲不是一个好母亲
His mum is not a very good mum.
不幸的是 他的父母抛弃了他
His parents abandoned him, unfortunately.
所以杰弗里生命的头两个月
So, for the first two months of Geoffrey's life,
他必须生活在恒温箱里
he had to live in an incubator.
杰弗里小时候很像一只被拔了毛的小鸡
Geoffrey started off like a little plucked chicken,
然后他长出了
and then he started getting
针头一般的羽毛
his pin feathers coming through,
长出了一点尾巴
you'll get a little bit of a tail come through,
然后通常它会开始长得有点像莫霍克头型
and then you normally get a little bit of a Mohawk.
他每天大概要长10%的体重
They put on about 10% of weight every day.
必须手把手的喂三个月
Takes three months of hand rearing.
然后重要的是要花一年的
And then on top of that, you've got up to a year
时间照看它们
of looking after them.
杰弗里最后长出了非常好看的红色羽毛 非常非常好看的深红色
Geoffrey came out beautiful red, beautiful, beautiful deep red.
杰弗里 你是杰弗里么？
Geoffrey? Are you Geoffrey?
旁白：杰弗里这种种类的金刚鹦鹉濒临灭绝
NARRATOR: Geoffrey's species of Macaw is in trouble.
现有的数量和原先的相比只是非常少的一部分
The wild population is only a fragment of what it once was.
哥斯达黎加是它们最后的要塞之一
Costa Rica is one of the last strongholds.
ARA希望能够阻止它们的灭绝
ARA hopes to stop the extinction
通过让杰弗里这样的鹦鹉回归野外
by repopulating the wild
以增加种类数量
with birds like Geoffrey.
他们最近才放生了7只
They recently released a group of seven macaws.
杰弗里是下一只
Geoffrey will be next.
迷糊不清的谈话
[Indistinct conversation]
卡斯尔斯：我们已经放了
CASTLES: We've released
100多只绯红金刚鹦鹉 我们有
over 100 scarlet macaws, and we've had
超过85%的存活率
over 85% survival rate.
让它们学会怎么在野外生存的
Part of the process of them
过程之一
learning how to survive in the wild
是教它们吃东西
is teaching the birds what to eat.
生物学家瑞秋和查理
The biologists Rachel and Charlie
正在出去
are going round
收集像海核桃
and they're collecting things like beach almonds,
珊瑚豆荚之类的
finding coral pods,
所有的这些食物都会让鸟们
all of the foods the birds are going to have to
学会怎么生存
learn to survive off.
你会看见他们把一整个树枝放在鸟笼里
You'll see them put whole branches in the aviary,
这样能让鸟们意识到
and that's so the birds can recognize,
“哦 这种树叶意味着这种食物”
"Oh, this leaf means this food."
它们嚼这些东西 发现
They start chewing on things,finding out
水果的哪一部分或者是果子的哪一部分好吃
what part of the fruit or the seed tastes good.
大部分是因为天性 很多鸟
A lot of it's instinct, so a lot of them actually will
第一次都会选核桃
pick up an almond for the first time and go,
“哦 我知道怎么打开它 很好玩”
"Oh, yeah, I know how to crack this, that's fun."
这基本上是新兵训练营
It's boot camp, basically.
金刚鹦鹉的新兵训练营
Macaw boot camp.
莉兹：我们要去度假
LIZ: We were going on vacation
我要想想怎么处理巴斯尔
and I was trying to figure out what to do with Basil.
我有一个朋友也有一只
I have a friend who also has
黄颈亚马逊鹦鹉
a yellow-naped Amazon.
所以我提议把它带上
So, I offered to take him.
莉兹：巴斯尔在我养他的这15年中
LIZ: Basil had never seen another yellow-naped Amazon
从来没见过另一只黄颈金刚鹦鹉
in the 15 years I'd owned him.
鸟叫
[Birds groaning]
旁白：莉兹和霍利决定在这些鸟身上赌一把
NARRATOR: Liz and Holly decide to take a gamble with the birds.
当哈特曼夫妇度假归来时
By the time the Hartmans returned from vacation,
巴斯尔和可可
Basil and Koko
关系已经很紧密了
were tightly bonded.
莉兹：我们把它放进旅行用笼子中
LIZ: We loaded him into his travel cage
开始把他带走时
and started to walk out of the house with him,
她的鹦鹉在笼子里走来走去 嘴里说着不
and her Amazon just starts pacing back and fourth going no!
可可在说“不！不！”
[Koko squawking, "No! No!" ]
米勒：你可以听见可可在叫
MILLER: You could hear Koko calling
就像他失去了他最好的朋友
like he was losing his best friend.
我们都哭了
We were in tears,
我们说 哦 我们不能让这样的事情发生
we said, oh, we can't have this happen,
这太令人伤心了
this is heartbreaking.
我开始和霍利说
I starting talking to Holly
问她愿不愿意领养巴斯尔
about whether she would adopt Basil.
她说愿意
So, she said yes.
你不能把你朋友送走
You can't just give away a friend.
你不能那么做
You just can't do that.
我很有负罪感
LIZ: I had a huge amount of guilt.
你接纳了这个生物
You take on this living creature,
你就有责任
it's your responsibility.
我们不是不想要巴斯尔了
It's not that we wanted to give up Basil,
巴斯尔过得也不好
the kids were having a hard time.
莉兹：他只是一只普通的野生的鸟
LIZ: He's just being a normal, wild bird.
你可以把他放到宠物店里
you can put them in a pet shop,
你可以给他们打扮
you can dress it up all you want,
但是他们依旧不是宠物
they're not pets.
现在 如果你去看看
Now, when you go over there and see them,
他们两个是非常好的朋友
they're best buddies.
鸟在咕咕叫
[Birds cooing]
我肯定不会再养鹦鹉了
I definitely would not have a parrot again.
我不会再养了 不 从我自己的心理健康
I would never do it again, no, for my own mental health,
和鹦鹉的心理健康来说
and the mental health of the parrot.
不
No.
旁白：在隔离区呆了一个月后
NARRATOR: After a month in quarantine,
卢被证明健康没问题
Lou is given a clean bill of health.
温莎：然后我们开始
WINDSOR: Then we begin the process of trying to
把他和其他的鸟放在一起
integrate him with other birds.
在野外他们有一整个雨林
In the wild they have an entire rainforest,
他们可以选择他们的伴侣
they can choose their own mate.
如果你把他们和不是他们选择的鸟放在一起
You put them together with birds that are not of their choice,
经常行不通
and it just doesn't always work.
旁白：他们一开始把卢放在大鸟鸟舍外面
NARRATOR: They start Lou outside a large aviary.
从这里 他可以看见其他的风头鹦鹉
From here, he can watch the other cockatoos
隔着一个安全距离
from a safe distance.
在外面呆了三周以后
After three weeks on the outside,
是时候让卢进入鸟舍了
it's time for Lou to move into the aviary.
因为不知道卢的过去 他们只能猜测
Without knowing Lou's past, they can only guess,
看着 祈祷着
and watch, and hope.
温莎：卢是很安静内敛的
WINDSOR: Lou, he's a little on the quiet and reserved side,
我们必须非常小心的挑选他的鸟舍伴侣
we had to very carefully pick his aviary mates.
他需要一个没有攻击性的
He needed non-aggressive,
一只温顺的鸟舍伴侣
you know, kind of docile aviary mates,
所以这是我们为他挑选的鸟舍
and so that's what we set up for him,
一个有着5只其他风头鹦鹉的鸟
an aviary with five other cockatoos.
旁白：在鸟舍里呆了两个星期后
NARRATOR: After two weeks inside the enclosure,
他们觉得现在把卢从笼子里拿出来很安全了
they feel it's safe to take Lou from his cage.
嗨 伙计
Hi, buddy.
你没事的
You're okay!
上去吧
Here you go, buddy! Oh!
好孩子
Oh, good boy!
旁白：然后令人没想到的事发生了
NARRATOR: And then the unexpected.
另一只孤独的风头鹦鹉
Another lone cockatoo,
公主 一只腿上有伤历史不明的鹦鹉
Princess, a parrot with an injured foot and a hazy history,
碰了碰运气
takes a chance.
在哥斯达黎加
In Costa Rica,
杰弗里的大日子终于要来了
Geoffrey's big day is finally here.
卡斯尔斯：能够看着你养的动物
CASTLES: Being able to see animals that you've raised,
自由 被放生 这是很重要的
free and wild, this is the ultimate.
你心里会担心
You do have that worry in the back of your mind,
如果他们过得不好没能幸存怎么办？
what happens if it doesn't go well and he doesn't survive?
看见没？ 那时你要去的地方
See? That's where you're going soon.
卡斯尔斯：不可能他们所有鸟都会活下来
CASTLES: It's not likely that all of them are gonna survive.
捕食者 意外
Predators, accidents.
你不能预测接下来要发生的事
You can't predict what they're gonna do
而且通常是你最喜欢的
and it's always the favorite ones
可能会死去
that you think are gonna get lost.
过来杰弗里 杰弗里 过来杰弗里
Come on Geoffrey, Geoffrey! Come on, Geoffrey!
当鸟在笼子里生活了一段时间后
Once the birds have lived in the cage for x-amount of time,
可以是2个月 也可以是6个月
it can be two months or it could be six months,
取决于换毛 取决于它们多久能适应
depending molts, depending on how quickly they adapt,
取决于时间 食物数量
the time of year, the food availability.
当所有的这些因素都好时
When all those factors are right,
就是我们开始放生的时候了
that's when we begin the release.
我们一只只的放生
We release the birds individually,
以确保它们每一只的生存条件都是平等的
so we can make sure each bird has an equal chance of survival.
他们要让杰弗里出来了
They're gonna let Geoffrey out,
他们要把它引到盒子里
they're gonna tempt him into the box,
或者想把--杰弗里很狡猾
or try to -- he's quite cunning.
杰弗里 这是你自由的机会
Geoffrey, this is your chance at freedom, mate.
最少要花好几个小时
It can take at least a few hours
让正确的鸟进到盒子里
to get the right bird in the box.
我会在那放点食物
I'll put a pile of food in there.
一旦杰弗里进到盒子里
And once they have Geoffrey in the box,
他们会让它安静的吃自己的食物
they'll let him eat his food in peace and quiet.
他准备好走了
He's ready to go!
他把他所有核桃都吃完了
He's eaten all his almonds.
这时他们会把外面的门放下来
That's when they'll let the outside door down.
有时我们发现外面的鸟
Quite often we find that the birds outside
进来 有时会它们会打架
come in, and there's a big scrap.
这会很有意思的
This is gonna be interesting.
杰弗里现在有了一个优势
Geoffrey has now got the advantage
他有这些外面的鸟
of having these outside birds established.
它们卖弄了一下
They show off quite a bit
实际上它们在教笼子里鸟
and they're actually teaching the birds in the aviary,
“看看我能做什么”之类的
"look what I can do," you know,
“你们以后也能这么做”
"you're going to be able to do this soon."
它们可以向它们展示哪里有吃的
They're going to be able to help show them where to eat,
教它们怎么做
teach them what to do,
给它们展示怎么飞翔
show them how to fly.
杰弗里 我希望他能适应鸟群
Geoffrey, I'm hoping will, just fit into the flock
每只鸟都觉得他很棒
and everybody will think he's awesome.
我们要做最好的期望 这是你能做的
We'll have to hope for the best, and that's all you can do.
好运 伙计
Good luck mate,
这是你的大日子
this is your big shot.
他飞得很好
He's a good flyer.
他最多在笼子里能活45-50岁
It would be far worse for him to live 45-50 years in captivity
比在野外惨多了
than to have a chance at living life in the wild.
我希望他能讨到好老婆有许多小孩
I hope he has a nice missus and lots of babies --
在野外能活得又长又开心
a long happy life in the wild.
我对所有的鹦鹉都这么希望 不止是杰弗里
And that's what I wish for all of them, not just for Geoffrey.
想了解更多“自然”计划
To learn more about what you've seen on this "Nature" program,